Milk teeth are very important milestone in child's life.
But do we all know that why they are extremely important
and what functions do they play in child's life, in child's development?
Here we have a master of pediatric dentist, Dr. Himali.
She will explain us and guide us through the entire process of oral hygiene and care in infants and kids.
Please note these all the tips are applicable from a newborn baby till your child is 6 years old
Because that's the most important part of child's developmental years
Let's get started
Okay, hello everyone
So now let's talk about milk teeth
What are milk teeth and why are they important?
So the first and foremost, milk teeth
They are also known as deciduous teeth, primary teeth
These are the commonly heard terms that are from the doctors, dentists or even from your relatives
They are also known as pearly whites.
Now let's dive into understanding why are milk teeth important?
Are they really important?
Because we have been hearing this since ages.
Like milk teeth they will as it is fall off.
Why are you taking care of them?
Let them be the way they are.
Yeah.
So let's understand the importance of milk teeth.
So the first and foremost importance of milk teeth is chewing.
So when your kid or your child or your baby is still 6 years.
the only teeth that are present in the mouth are the milk teeth so maximum chewing maximum biting
is happening by the milk teeth now consider your child is not having milk teeth that are in healthy
condition that is they are carious they are having big big holes or anything like that what will
happen your child will start eating different food with different consistencies once your child was
eating hard now your child will switch to food that is a little semi-solid or like mashy food
something in which he does not have to chew, directly will gulp food or your child will start
pouching food everywhere. Is that healthy for your child? Not at all. We need to understand one thing
that brain development is happening maximum until the age of six years. So this is the time when
your child needs to bite, needs maximum nutrition or probably if you're giving some added nutrition
even that is needed. So if it's there and if we cannot take care of our milk teeth, so in turn we
are harming the development of our child. Then coming to the next thing, milk teeth are here
and we have the permanent teeth that are sitting behind the milk teeth. So these milk teeth help
the permanent teeth or guide them to come in that position. You might have noticed that a milk tooth
is there and right in that position a permanent tooth comes. So if the milk tooth is not there
or if the milk tooth is removed early or it's very carious, in such cases what happens is that the
permanent teeth might get confused inside. It might come more towards the tongue or it might
come more towards the cheek. Or in some cases, the permanent teeth might not erupt. It might
just be locked inside the jaw. We do not want that, right? Coming to the next most important
thing of milk teeth that it does. And we don't even know it does it very silently. Did you know
that speech is something that is affected by teeth? We never thought about it. Now come on,
Let's tell these some words or some letters with me.
Tell V.
V.
P.
F.
Tell L.
L.
Th.
Now imagine telling these letters without the teeth.
I can't say Th.
V.
We will never tell V.
Now tell L.
It doesn't sound.
L.
L without your teeth.
So this is basically you need your front teeth for proper speech.
If you do not have them, what will happen?
your child will start lisping or your child will start stammering all of which will in turn affect
your child's self-esteem in public plus speech development will be delayed which is another
problem that you will face now coming to the next thing that a milk tooth can do so milk tooth even
plays a very important role in the aesthetics of your child so now we all know that one smile can
win millions of hearts but what if that smile is only not nice what if the smile is black
it's crooked or what if the teeth are only not there and then when your smile child smiles you
know there is a little social pressure in children's as well kids around will start
teasing your kid and in turn he will have very low self-esteem it's really necessary to understand
and not only kids i'm sure even family members do tease the kid who does not have teeth so we take
it in a very fun way but for kids who have peer pressure around we do not take it in a fun way
so it's always advised to have a healthy smile and if not get it restored so that your child's
speech as well as aesthetics is taken into concern and development definitely all of us as a parents
we really want to understand that they are important so we have to take care of this
so all of you we both together are not going to confuse you we are going to in fact lead you
step-by-step guide that how do you actually do it so all of you let's see you all in the next segment
infant oral care so what do we do and how do we do with respect to infants about their oral care
let's get started